<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oppression under the colour of law, or, My Lord Hercarse, his new new praticks as a way for peaceable subjects to be ware of pleying [sic] with a hot spirited Lord of the Session so far as is possible when arbitrarie government is in the dominion / published by Mr. Robert Pittilloh.</title>
            <author>Pittilloh, Robert, 1621?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10594932</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10594932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Oppression under the colour of law, or, My Lord Hercarse, his new new praticks as a way for peaceable subjects to be ware of pleying [sic] with a hot spirited Lord of the Session so far as is possible when arbitrarie government is in the dominion / published by Mr. Robert Pittilloh.</title>
                  <author>Pittilloh, Robert, 1621?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harcarse, Roger Hog, --  Lord, 1635?-1700.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45333:1"/>
            <p>OPPRESSION UNDER THE COLOUR OF LAW, OR, MY LORD HERCARSE HIS NEW PRATICKS</p>
            <p>As a Way-marke for Peaceable SUBJECTS to be ware of Pleying with a hot Spirited Lord of the Seſſion, ſo far as is Poſſible when Arbitrarie Government is in the Dominion.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS 20. verſe 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>An Inheritance may be gotten haſtily at the beginning, but the end thereof ſhall not be Bleſſed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>ROBERT PITTILLOH,</hi> Advocat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45333:2"/>
            <head>OPPRESSION under colour of LAW, OR, My Lord HERCARSE his New Practicks; Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloch Advocat.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>As a way to make for Peaceable Subjects to beware of pleying with a hot Spirited Lord of the Seſſion, ſo far as poſſible, when Arbitrary Government is in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Proverbs 20. verſe 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>An inheritance may be gotten haſtily at the beginning, but the end ſhall not be bleſſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hiles in my Solitary thoughts, I began to conſider the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Juſtice, (which conſiſts in <hi>individno</hi>) reckoned by the Learned among the principal Cardinal Vertues, and of Judgement, which is the Lords, and of the long tract of Judicial ſentences paſt againſt me, in an Affair depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt me, at the inſtance of <hi>Alexander Ayton</hi> of <hi>Inchdarnie,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the inſtance of Sir <hi>Roger Hoge,</hi> perſonated by <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> his Son in Law, and how the weakneſs of my Judgment could not comply with the ſaid Procedour as juſt and juſtifiable either in the Root or Branch: I conceived it moſt agreeable to my Duty, to expoſe the ſame to the view of the World, that perſons judicious and impartial may either convince me to a full Submiſſion, if I be wrong, or the Authors of my ſuffering to change their courſe; Seeing in the multitude of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelours there is Stability: And as that Noble young Man, <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaid, <hi>Wiſdom is not alwayes with the Ancient, nor underſtanding with the Men of days, but there is a ſpirit in Man, and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth knowledge.</hi> However, ſeeing he that doth Truth comes to the Light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, they are wrought in GOD. I hope none has reaſon to be offended with the open and plain laying forth of the Truth in this matter.</p>
            <p>And therefore to come to the purpoſe, The caſe is thus, in <hi>Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1648 Lieutenant General <hi>Ruthven</hi> then Heritor of the lands of <hi>Killernie,</hi> and <hi>Andrew Wardlaw</hi> appearand Heir to the ſaids Lands, and Reverſer upon the payment of 17500 Merks <hi>Scots</hi> borrowed from <hi>Archibald
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45333:3"/>Stuart.</hi> Brother German to the then Laird of <hi>Roſeſyth</hi> 6000 Merks, and from <hi>Alexander</hi> his Brother 4000 Merks, for which the ſaid Leiutenant General, <hi>Andrew Wardlaw</hi> the Appearand Heir, and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wardlaw</hi> his Siſter, then Spouſe to the ſaid Leiutenant G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neral, gave to each of them an heritable Bond, Oblieging themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nctly and ſeverally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make payment to them of the ſaid Sums, and all cu rent Annual Rents; And for their better ſecurity, oblieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with one Conſent and Aſſent, to Infeft each of them, in an Annual Rent correſponding to their reſpective ſums, to be uplifted forth of the ſaids Lands. Hereupon by vertue of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts contained in them, the ſaid two Brethren obtained themſelves infeft ſeverally in the ſaids Lands, the 26 of <hi>May</hi> thereafter; And received from Leiutenant General <hi>Ruthven,</hi> one years Annual rent of the ſaid ſums, from the date of the Bond, till <hi>Whitſunday</hi> 1649. <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> her Husband dying ſhortly thereafter, <hi>Andrew Wardlaw</hi> the Reverſer entered in poſſeſſion of the whole Eſtate, by the tollerance of the two Brothers Creditors; the Law being patent to them to have exacted their Annual Rents, in regard <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> the Conjunct Fiar was unwilling to ſtop them; and <hi>Andrew Wardlaw</hi> her Brother had no pretence to impede them. But the ſaid two Brothers complying with <hi>Andrew Wardlaw,</hi> and intending to bend all their forces againſt <hi>Margaret</hi> the Conjunct Fiar, charged <hi>William Ruthven</hi> lawful Son and appearand Heir to Leiutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Ruthven</hi> to enter Heir to his Father, and ſhe obtained Decreet againſt him: They charged <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> then a Widow, to make payment to them of the principal Sumes, bygone Annual Rents, and Penalty; And likewiſe, they charged <hi>Andrew Wardlaw,</hi> but never inſiſted againſt him, to the outmoſt Diligence, tho he never ſuſpended them, and was in poſſeſſion of the whole Eſtate But <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> was forced both for her Son <hi>William Ruthven,</hi> and for her ſelf to ſuſpend their Charge; And ſo far was ſhe from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peding them to uplift the Annual Rents, that this is one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Reaſons in her Suſpenſion, <hi>That the Chargers were aboundantly ſecured in their Annual Rents, by their Infeftments; and that they or ſome others in their names were in poſſeſſion.</hi> Which ſhe had Reaſon to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon the Tollerance abovementioned. And the Reaſons in her Sons is, <hi>He being a Child, the Lands were patent, for appryzing, and he had no other means wherewith to ſatisfie them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45333:3"/>
            <p>The Sums being thus rendred moveable by the Charge given to <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Margaret Wardlaws,</hi> perſonally oblieged to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the Decreet obtained againſt <hi>William Ruthven</hi> her Son: <hi>Archibald <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuart</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1654, aſſigned his ſum to <hi>Alexander</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Principal and Annual Rent and Penalty, with the whole Heads and Chuſes contained in his Bond, and Inſtrument of Seaſing fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thereupon; Whereupon in <hi>June</hi> 1654, the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed the ſaids Lands, for Principal, Annual Rents, and Sherriff-Fie; and obtained himſelf Infeſt upon his Appriſing under the great Seal; but never inſiſted either for their Annual Rents, or for Mails and Duties, ſo long as their Comorad <hi>Andrew Wardlaw</hi> was in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: Knowing that the Ground was lyable to them for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuals, and they being Young Men having no Charge but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, living with their Mother, who entertained them on her Charity. Hereupon <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> ſeing that a daily burden was running on upon her Conjunct-fie Lands; and that ſhe had got nothing, but was forced to live upon her Credit: Warned her Brother to remove, and at length after much Oppoſition obtained a Decreet of Removing againſt him, but never made uſe thereof till the year 1656, after that he and Mr. <hi>Robert Pitt. Iloch</hi> her preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Husband had ſeveral Friendly communings upon the Affair, And afterwards a full Submiſſion drawn betwixt them: Mr. <hi>John Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> of <hi>Leno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> Arbitrator for him, and one <hi>George Knox</hi> then a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Collector, Arbitrator for her, and Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloch</hi> her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Husband. But upon ſight of her Claim, he and his Arbitrator brake up the Submiſſion <hi>reinf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cta,</hi> whereupon at length ſhe was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to put her Decreet in Execut, or otherwiſe to live perquire, and the Annual Rents to run on likewayes.</p>
            <p>This being done, <hi>Alexander Stewart</hi> founding upon his Appry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Concourſe of her Brother, purſued her and her preſent Husband with all Rigour for Mails and Duties: Whereupon offer was made to him of a Localitie for his Annualtents during all the time of her Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, and in time comming; Which he refuſed to accept, unleſs we would ſatisfie him for all bygones, which (as they then told him) they judged moſt unreaſonable; in regard ſhe had gotten nothing her ſelf for the time bygone: And ſhe being but a Liferentrix, might dye before ever ſhe received as much as would ſatisfie their bygone Annualrents. And it is referred
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45333:4"/>to the conſideration of all Judicious Readers whither this was not a Rational offer, ſeing they had layen out of their Annualrents, not only through their own fault, (the Laws being patent) But alſo they themſelves had concured with her Brother, to keep her of Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, producing their rights to furniſh him with Defences, and reaſon of Suſpenſion againſt her. And as to the truth of it, it is te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitified by their own Decreet, obtained for proving the Tennor of a Diſpoſition granted by <hi>James Bailly</hi> to Lieutenent General <hi>Ruthven;</hi> Wherein this is made uſe of, as one of their Reaſons for proving that Tennor, That Mr. <hi>Robert Pittiloch</hi> offered them a Localitie for their Annualrents. But this being refuſed ſhe was forced to raiſe a <hi>Summonds of Reduction</hi> againſt them of their Apptiſing and whole grounds thereof, Whereupon in <hi>December</hi> 1658, ſhe obtained a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, Reducing, Retreating and Anulling</hi> the Bands whereupon the Appriſing is founded, in ſo far as they perſonally oblige the ſaid <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> with all Decreets of Appryſings, Charters, Seaſings, Decreets of removing following thereupon; But ſuſtaining them, <hi>Quoad</hi> the real Right; in regard of her conſent, to the Precept and Procuratrie for <hi>Infeftment.</hi> This being done, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſer never contraverted in his time, but the Appryſing was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>quo ad eam,</hi> and perſued for a poinding of the Ground, only for his Annualrents: In Oppoſition to which. <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> the Defender and her preſent Husband, conſidering they might in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Equity, uſe all Legal Defences for ſtoping this Procedor, in reſpect of the offer of payment during her Poſſeſſion, and that they themſelves were the cauſe of there not being payed, Firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to improve their Executions which accordingly they did: Whereupon their Action was for a conſiderable time delayed, Thereafter the Proceſs was loſt, whereupon it delayed another while: After this <hi>Archibald</hi> died, and after him <hi>Alexander,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after Mr. <hi>William Bailie</hi> pretended an lutereſt, which if it had been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, would have deſtroyed the Intereſt both of Purſuers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, which was taken away by proving the Tennor of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, granted by his Father to <hi>Lieutenent General Ruthven,</hi> after-this <hi>Alexander</hi> being dead, his Son <hi>James Stewart</hi> ſucceeded to him, and he not being ſatisfied with Annualrents, with concourſe of his Mother <hi>Katrine Drummond</hi> his Tutrix purſued for Mails and Deuties: To which the Decreet of Reduction abovementioned was always
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45333:4"/>opponed, and as oft ſuſtained: Yea when her Perſonal obligation was aledged to be ſortified upon this ground, <hi>Ob non repugnantiam.</hi> It was repelled as a quible: The <hi>Lords</hi> finding it was not the duty of a wife to repugne her Husbands deeds. But after all this and a long tract of time; <hi>James Stewart</hi> and his Tutrix both died, whereupon the Heritable right founded upon the Appryſing fell in to <hi>William Stewart</hi> (now of <hi>Roſſyth</hi>) Cuſing German to <hi>James,</hi> and the bygone Annualrents to <hi>Jean Stewars,</hi> Lady <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> his Fathers Siſter, who aſſigned them to <hi>Alexander Aiton</hi> of <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> her ſon, and Son in Law to Sir <hi>Roger Hoge</hi> then Lord <hi>Hercarſe,</hi> one of the <hi>Lords of Seſſion.</hi> But before this right fell into them, at leaſt before it was declared, (the ſame being interrupeed by a long conteſt betwixt them and <hi>Alexander Naiper,</hi>) Mr. <hi>Robert Pitilloh</hi> and his Wife entered in terms of Agreement with <hi>William Stewart</hi> of <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> who had right to the expired Appryſing, and to all Annualrents that were due ſince the death of <hi>James Stewart</hi> his Cuſing German: Laying out to him the favourableneſs of their condition, in that <hi>Margaret Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law</hi> was both Conjunctfiar of the ſaids Lands by her firſt Husband, and Apparent Heir to them by her Father, who was Proprietar of them, which the ſaid Laird of <hi>Roſsyth</hi> reliſhed very well: And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times promiſed he ſhould never agree with any till we had the firſt offer. But we fearing that the Annualrents would be declared to belong to <hi>Inchdarine</hi> Son in Law to a Lord of the <hi>Seſſion;</hi> who might do great things for him, (as it after fell out) were loath to give too much upon conſideration of this Danger: Whereupon we continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtill willing to the Bargain, but conferring upon the price for a long time, without any finall Agreement; till the right of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nualrents came in <hi>Inchdarnies</hi> perſon: And then my <hi>Lord Hercarſe,</hi> ſent for Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloch,</hi> entertaining him with fair Language enough, but withall with many pumping Queſtions anent the Lands of <hi>Killernie</hi> and the condition thereof: Which I confeſs I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with more Ingenuitie then Prudence, conceiving at that time all he ſpoke to me had flowed from the like Principles; and among other things he mentioned to me agreement with him for the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone Annualrents: To which I anſwered I could not agree as the caſe then ſtood for two Reaſons. 1ſt. It would be an Homologating of <hi>Roſſyths</hi> Right. <hi>2dly,</hi> My wife being but an <hi>Liferentrix</hi> If I ſhould agree for the Annualrents without the Heritable Right; My Wife
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45333:5"/>might die long before I were ſatisfied of what I ſhould Deburſe: But I was in terms with <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> for the Heritable Right, and I ſhe and I ſhould agree for that, I would indeavour likewayes to agree for ſuch Annualrents as were juſtly due; And in order thereto with all diligence met with <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> and finally agreed with him, to give him 12000 <hi>Merks</hi> for his whole Intereſt, concerning which write was to be drawn with the firſt convenience; It being then late at night. After which a Gentleman of Credit and honeſty, told me that to morrow thereafter, he overheard a Servant belonging to <hi>Hercarſe</hi> ſaying to a friend of <hi>Roſſyths,</hi> that their 10000 <hi>Merks</hi> was better then my 12000 <hi>Merks,</hi> indeavouring hereby to take the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain out of my hand. But conceaving it to be below any honeſt Man, and farr more below a <hi>Lord of the Seſſion,</hi> to take ſuch baſe and indirect methods, after I had told him I was in terms with <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyth</hi> therefore: And after that the buſineſs was fully ended, with which he declared himſelf noways unſatisfied, as alſo my Son in Law <hi>Mr. William Hoge</hi> having ingenuouſly told him the ſame thing, adding, he hoped his Lordſhip would not play in our Game: Whereupon he gave him aſſurance he would not, but that he would cauſe his Son in Law quite as much as <hi>Roſſyth</hi> had done and more, I ſlighted the Gentlemans Information and friendly Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition altogether; However I went down to <hi>Roſſyth</hi> and payed him a viſite, in whom I found no change, only I obſerved <hi>Innermey</hi> and his <hi>Lady</hi> to abide cloſe by him while I was in his companie, after which my Son in Law who was his Intimat, and had done him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſpecial Services, went to him and deſired that what was agreed upon might be drawn in Write; to whom his anſwer was. Do ye thing me ſo baſe and unworthie a Raſcal as that I will alter what I have done. Whereupon we reſted, not making great haſte; But quickly thereafter we were alarmed with ſurpriſing News, that <hi>My Lord Hercarſe, Inchdarnie, Innermey,</hi> and ſome others, had meet with <hi>Roſſyth</hi> in <hi>Widdow Thomſons</hi> houſe, near his Lodging, and he had granted a Diſpoſition to <hi>Inchdarine</hi> of his hail Right for the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage and all Annualrents whatſoever he had right to; which we find ſince verified by the Diſpoſition granted to him, with conſent of <hi>Innermey, Scotſtown</hi> his Brother in Law, and his <hi>Lady,</hi> of the date the to of <hi>December,</hi> 1687. Whereupon he was Infeft the 29 of the ſaid Moneth thereafter.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45333:5"/>
               <head>Some Reflections upon this Bargain,</head>
               <head type="sub">It is humblie offered to the Conſideratian of the Judicious Reader, whither this was not Concuſſion in <hi>Uberiore forma</hi> in this Buſſineſs?</head>
               <p>FOr clearing whereof, we are to conſider, <hi>1mo.</hi> The qualities and Condition of <hi>Roſſyth</hi> the granter of this Diſpoſition. <hi>2do.</hi> The qualities and Condition of <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> to whom the Diſpoſition was granted <hi>formaliter. 3tio.</hi> The Qualifications and Condition of my L. <hi>Hercarſe,</hi> Preſent, Advyſing, Perſwading, and bringing the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to a Concluſion. As to the firſt, it is well known, <hi>Roſſyth</hi> is amongſt the moſt ancient Barrons in <hi>Fife,</hi> (if not the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient) and of a moſt Honourable Deſcent, and alſo a Gentleman who underſtands his own buſineſs conſiderably well. <hi>2do,</hi> The Bargain he had made with me was not raſhaly contrived nor made uſe of upon a Surpriſal, but after many Conferrences and Friendly meetings had for the purpoſe at ſeveral of which, his Advocate Mr. <hi>John Stewart</hi> was preſent. <hi>3tio,</hi> After it was cloſed the expreſſion abovementioned, which he uſed to my Son in Law, who had done him ſeveral ſingular Services, inſinuats he judged none but a baſe and unworthy Raſcal, would reſell from a Buſſineſs ſo fullie ended and concluded: But laſtly it is to be conſidered he was a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in diſtreſs, and under many burdens of Debt to ſeveral Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, and he had one great Action depending before the Lords of Seſſion for a great Summ of Money, which would have much contributed for his relief, and concerning the delay whereof I have heard him often complain. As to the ſecond it is well known <hi>Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dairnie</hi> was in no condition of himſelf to do him any Service; but only by my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his Father in Law, and it is well known he was neither ſo Skilful in Rhetorick, nor Fluent in Oratorie, that thereby he could effectuate any great Matter: But as to the third, it is as well known that my <hi>Lord Herearſe</hi> is a Perſon who has been bred in Sciences from his Youth, Skilled in the Law, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45333:6"/>for his preſent Condition he was then a Lord of the Seſſion, and reckoned among thoſe of the firſt Magnitude, and a man of a moſt forward Inclination in Prolecuting or Buſſneſs, whether for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or his Friend; as alſo, he was a Lord of the Court of Juſticiary, which was a Court moſt terrible to many in that day, and by which Court <hi>Walter Stewart, Reſſythes</hi> nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſman and appear and <hi>Heir,</hi> and ſeveral others in whom he had a ſpecial Intereſt were declared Fugi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ives. Which being Conſidered, it is offered to the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Readers, whither this was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Concuſſion in the higheſt Degree? which by the Doctors of the Civil Law, is defined to be <hi>Crimen quo ſub pretextu poteſtatis quam quis h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>het terror injicitur pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae vel rei alterius extorquendi cauſa, &amp;c.</hi> And if it be not a Concuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the worſt nature, in ſo far as hereby a Gentleman of Ancient Extract, great Credit and Honour, has been perſwaded contrair to his Faith and Ingadgement to Violat his Obligation. So deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately perfected and adhered to for ſome dayes therea ter. And in ſo far as it was likewiſe done contrair to the Laws of Gratitude in ſo far as concerned <hi>Mr. William Hoge,</hi> for whoſe Children the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe eſpecially was made, for whoſe cauſe he often decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red he wold give me a Thouſand Merks down of the Pryce; And in ſo far as it was done by a Lord of the Seoſſin, who ſhould have been a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Patron of Juſtice, and that accompanyed with the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances abovementioned: And alſo whither herein there was not Money given by <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> upon this power and terror injected? in ſo far as the Bargain was granted for a Thouſaud Merks leſs then <hi>Mr Robert Pittilloch</hi> ſhould have given for it, beſides an other Thouſand merks which <hi>Roſſyth</hi> declared he gave down, out of his reſpect to <hi>Mr. William Hoge;</hi> To all which may be added, ſuch was his Confidence of Effectuating his Purpoſe, <hi>Terrore ſuo; et plena po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate quam tune habuit,</hi> that the Summonds was raiſed, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, for the Annualrents in <hi>Roſſyths</hi> name; before this Bargain was made, without his knowledge or conſent as he declared to me himſelf ſeveral times but leaving this to the Judicious Reader; we proceed;</p>
               <p>After this Bargain was ended, and the Summonds raiſed, and execute, in the name of <hi>Roſſyth</hi> and <hi>Inchdairnie,</hi> My Lord ſent for me the ſecond time, and when I came to him, he asked me, if I would ſatisfie them now for the Heretable Right, and all the bygone
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45333:6"/>Annualrents? To which I anſwered, looking upon this Motion as a Jear, I had once bought it alreadie, and his Son in Law had taken it over my head; I had no mind to buy it the ſecond time, and when I looked for a reply, carrying Reaſons to Juſtifie the deed; All he ſaid was, he had reaſon to doe for his own ſecuritie; which my weakeneſs could not comprehend, to be any better Juſtification, then if a Robber with an empty purſe, when he had taken one from his Neighbour, had told him, he behooved to do it for his own ſecuritie, in as much, as without Money he could not Travel: As likewiſe he told me, it would byd but one Bellum; which I looked upon as the higheſt of Threatnings, and therefore anſwered him with much Sobrietie, I could not help it; his Lordſhip knew the old Proverb, <hi>There was never a Lord of the Seſſion loſt a cauſe, and there never one of their Bairns wan one.</hi> Thus having parted from him, the Summonds being execute both for Mails and Deuties, and for Annualrents, die Summonds for Poinding the Ground was called upon the 6 day, which was the day of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peirance, contrair to the Pratick of the Houſe; which is not to call till the day of Compe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance be paſt: But as to the other for Mails and Duties, it was never yet publickly called, in the ordinar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor any of the two ſent out to be ſeen for ſix dayes, conform to the Laws of the Kingdom, Acts of Sederunt, and immemorial pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in ſuch caſes: But <hi>tam avide inhiarunt in legatum adventitium.</hi> which had hapened to <hi>Inchda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nie</hi> in an unexpected manner; that a new courſe was invented for a ſudden Diſpatch of the buſineſs: <hi>viz. Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darnie</hi> gave in a Bill of Suſpenſion, in name of the whole Tennants, ennumerating them by their names; and amongſt them one who was never a Tennant, <hi>viz. Robert Douglas</hi> Servant to <hi>Agnes Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng down their particular Duties, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, they were reſting the ſame for the Terms of <hi>Whitſunday</hi> &amp; <hi>Mertimaſs</hi> preceeding; and that they were to pay the ſame to any having beſt Right, but they were diſtreſſed by two ſeveral Parties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Bill being given up to ſee, theſe Anſwers were given to it <hi>verhatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Primo,</hi> If this Bill of Suſpenſion be granted, Writers to the <hi>Signet</hi> needs never hereafter to put in another reaſon of Suſpenſion, but <hi>ſie volo ſic jubeo;</hi> In ſo far as in the firſt place, this Bill is given in by <hi>Inchdarnie,</hi> not only without the conſent of the ſaids Tennents, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45333:7"/>after they have diſowned and diſclaimed the ſame, as prejudgeing them of all the Priviledges competent to them in an Ordinar Action which he has ſtated againſt them for the ſaids Mails and Duties: Which (as is humbly concevied) is a Forgerie; if not a Falſet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secundo,</hi> This Bill Lybels the Tennents, as acknowledging they are reſting their hail <hi>Mertimaſs Duties,</hi> and that they are willing to pay them to any of the ſaids Parties who ſhall be found to have beſt right thereto: Whereas they have truly payed them to the ſaid <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> and her Husband already, and received diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therefore, who has been their Maſters theſe 20. years bygone: And that before any diligence uſed by the other Party, to put them in <hi>Malafide,</hi> which (as is humbly conceived) ought likewayes to be looked upon as a ſecond Forgerie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertio,</hi> In this Bill the Tennents Duties are Lybelled, as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by them farr beyond what they are, and by ſome of them who pays no Dutie but two <hi>Shearers in Harveſt,</hi> for their ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Land, to be conſiderable ſumes of Money; which (as is humbly conceived) is a third Forgerie.</p>
               <p>And as to <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> Conjunct-fiar of the ſaids Lands, and her Husband, if ſuch a Bill ſhould be paſt, <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> having deviſed this project, and prepared all his Inſtructions for <hi>Summar</hi> diſcuſſing; they are moſt unjuſtly ſurpriſed, and hereby defrauded of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinar terms, competent to them in an ordinar Action: Which is the more odious in the perſon of <hi>Inchdarnie,</hi> Becauſe this is the firſt time that ever they heard he pretended an Intereſt in theſe Lands.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> If ſuch a Bill ſhould be paſt, it puts them in a condition never to uplift their Mails and Duties, albeit they ſhould looſe the Arreſtment; upon a meer Alledgance and pretence of perſons who never yet ſhewed any right thereto: Whereby if any of the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents prove <hi>lapſi bonis,</hi> they are loſt for ever.</p>
               <p>And if it ſhould be diſcuſſed upon the Bill, which <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> boſts he will obtain, it is a preparative of moſt dangerous conſequence; contrait to Law or Pratick, to diſcuſs <hi>Heritable Rights,</hi> in <hi>prima in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia</hi> upon an Bill of Suſpenſion: And if this ſhould be ſuſtained all ordinar Actions of greateſt concernment, may be brought from the <hi>Bench</hi> to the <hi>Side Barr,</hi> meerly upon a pretence, that the purſuer has a Competitor: Whereupon the Defender is defrauded both of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45333:7"/>his ordinary Dyets for proving his Defences: and the benefice of the Roll, ordained for the Leidges, that they may not be ſurpriſed in their juſt Defences competent to them in their ſeveral Actions. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t the Buſineſs was with the Son in Law of my <hi>Lord Hercarſe,</hi> which he was to finiſh with one <hi>Bellum;</hi> and none of the Anſwers were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and therefore we put in a Bill to the hail; Lords of the Tennor following;</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <p>MY Lords of Counſel and Seſſion, unto your Lordſhips, humbly Means and Shaws, we your Servitors <hi>Laurence Mudie, Adam Peacock, John Henderſon,</hi> and the Remnant Tennents of <hi>Killernie</hi> and <hi>Bandrum,</hi> That where there is a Bill of Suſpenſion given in to your Lordſhips, (we know not by whom) upon an alledged Double poynding, wherein we are alledged to acknowledge we pay great Duties, far beyond what ever we were in uſe to make payment of, and that we are reſting our Mertimaſs Dutie for the year laſt paſt <hi>1687.</hi> And that we alledge we are charged and purſued by <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Wardlaw</hi> and Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloh</hi> her Husband, for the ſaids Mails and Dueties, albeit not reſting by us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereupon <hi>Alexander Aſton</hi> of <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> intends to found a Proceſs againſt us, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloh</hi> and his Spouſe our Maſters. It is humbly repreſented to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, that if the ſaid Bill ſhall be ſuſtained as the foundation of a Proceſs as ſaid is, albeit diſclaimed and diſowned by us under our hands, yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> will make faith againſt us in time coming, whereby in the firſt place we ſhall be found lyable in far greater Mails and Dueties then ever were due by us, and the Mertimaſs Deutie laſt paſt already payed by us, to the ruin of us and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> poor Families. <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſhall be found guilty of accuſing of our ſaids Maſters of the hight of Covetouſneſs, in requiring our Duetie twice for one Term, which is a crime ſuperſcribed by the higheſt of all Judges, with the Name and Title of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> whereof we never knew them guilty.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore we humbly pray, that for preventing the utter ruin of our poor Fortunes, and our diſgrace in being purſued for ſlandring our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with ſo horrid a Crime, your Lordſhips would cauſe deliver up to us that Bill of Suſpenſion, as our own proper Evident to be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled and deſtroyed. Or if <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> ſhall be ſo far indulged that it ſhall be ſuſtained to him as a Foundation of a Proceſs, binding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and our Maſters above ſpecified, as ſaid is, he may be ordained to ſubſcrive che ſame before two witneſſes, and Judicially to abide thereat; that we may have the benefit of improving thereof
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45333:8"/>with concourſe of his <hi>Majeſties Advocate,</hi> as falſe and forged as accords of the Law.</p>
                     <p>This Bill being read to the hail Lords, the Deliverance on the back thereof, was written by the <hi>Clerk</hi> in theſe terms,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>Feb:</hi> 14: 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>THe Lords haveing heard this Petition remit to the Ordinar, to whom the within Bill of Suſpenſion was preſented, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the ſame to be given up to the Petitioners; or to be ſubſcrived by <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> or not as he ſhall find juſt. But my Lord Preſident refuſed to ſubſcrive it: Whereupon to morrow thereafter I waited upon his Lordſhip while he was upon the Bench; And after he had ended the Subſcriveing all his Interloquitors, and Subſcrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Deliverances upon other Bills, deſired his Lordſhip would Subſcrive this, ſhewing him the Ordinar would doe nothing on it, without his Subſcription: To which he anſwered, he remembered nothing of it, whereunto I replyed I was never known to be a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, and the Clerk whoſe carriage in all the Buſſineſs was honeſt, and impartial roſe up and owned it, whereupon he deſired me to move it to Morrow; and they would do ſomething in it: Which accordingly was done, and as I was informed, (for there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing put in Write) it was Verbalie recommended to my Lord <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> to whom the Bill was preſented. What the Reaſons of my Lord Preſidents refuſal were the Eminence of his Station and the Greatneſs of his Parts, forbids me by Conjecture to Determine, albeit in that day I judged it as much his Dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, as it was mine to require it. However neither the one nor the other was grant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, albeit the ſaid Bill was likewiſe diſclaimed by the Tennants pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, their Advocate <hi>Mr. William Hoge</hi> in their name diſowning the ſame at the Barr; But all was in vain, the Bill is ſuſtained: It was given in by my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his Son in Law. But becauſe neither the Anſwers given to the Bill of Suſpenſion, nor the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons given in in the Tennants Bill were reſpected; wee ſhall add ſome few Reaſons further, which we conceive could not but be known to the Lords themſelves, <hi>viz. 1mo,</hi> A Suſpenſion in its own natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is but a Dilatorie ſentence, as the word ſignifies, the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45333:8"/>upon the Bill imports, and the Sentence at Dicuſſing bears which is either, Finds the Letters orderly proceeded, or Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends the Letters ſimpliciter; and therefore where there is no charge the Suſpenſion is a Suſpending Nothing, and Nothing cannot be put to further Execution, if it be alledged his Rights gave him a ground of a Decreet; and therefore there was a charge in the Root, tho' there was no formal charge: It is anſwered, his rights were not then produced and judged of, and <hi>de non entibus &amp; non apparentibus idem datur judicium: 2do,</hi> If it ſhall be ſuſtained that perſons may give in a Bill of Suſpenſion whither the Debitors will or not, then any malicious perſon at his pleaſure may give in a Bill for Suſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Creditor, to provock him unneceſſarly to diſtreſs the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitor: Whereupon much trouble and diſtreſs might follow. If it be anſwered they have not an intereſt; it is replyed as formerly, whatſoever his Intereſt was, at that time when his Bill was ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it was not ſeen and conſidered by the Lords: But becauſe through the weakneſs of my Capacity, which could not ſwallow the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Teſts which other of profounder Judgments receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with full Satisfaction, I have been many years out of Practiſe, in which the Lords might have made many Acts of Sederunt, which makes ſuch <hi>Fictiones furis</hi> lawful, and Practicable. We ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt no more on thir: Adding only two more, which are founded upon pure Nature, and theſe Principles which GOD hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in all Mens hearts, The firſt is this Bill of Suſpenſion cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ought not to have been ſuſtained for the ground of a Decreet, againſt any but ſuch as were Tennants in the Lands, to which <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> pretended right: <hi>2do,</hi> Nor againſt them, for Sums or Duties which they were never reſting But ſo it is that upon this Bill, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Letters orderly proceeded thereon; Decreet was paſt at leaſt againſt one who was never Tennent in theſe Lands, &amp; againſt many of them for Sumes they were never due; Whereupon they were denunced, and upon Caption Incarcerat ten dayes in the To booth of <hi>Dunfermleng;</hi> The Lords having no other Inſtruction, either who were Tennen s, or what they were reſting, but <hi>Inchdairnies</hi> word therefore: Whoſe carriage truly was ſomewhat Scandelons when he came amongſt us, tho' his Authority was ſo great with the Lords: And if it ſhall be alledged to be the fault of the Writter who raiſed the Horning, It is anſwered, when a Bill was put in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45333:9"/>complaining of the Writter, and craving he might be puniſhed therefore, The Lords anſwer was, <hi>Finds the Writer has done no wrong.</hi> And therefore wee leave it to the Reader to conſider, where the wrong lay. Whereas they found out a remeed afterward for Liquidation and proveing the quantities, it ſhall have an anſwer in its own place. But as yet there was never any thing invented, for ſuccour of him who was no Tennent, ſeeing the order for the Tennents to compear and depone, could never oblidge ſuch as were no Tennents to compear and depone, nor can it in Reaſon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, why the Decreet might not as well have paſſed againſt the whole Parioch, if <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> had lybelled them Tennants, the reaſon being one and the ſame as to one and to many.</p>
               <p>But the Bill being ſuſtained, tho the Lords were far advanced in their Roll of Suſpenſions; Yea ſo fat that it would not have tempted any ordinar Mans patience, to have waited till it had come in in the ordinar Courſe, yet the reaſons of this behoved to be diſcuſſed on the Bill; (it was to abide but one Bellum) for which a Bill was put in by <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> to the Lords, which receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed anſwer in theſe Termes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>January,</hi> 21 1688.</head>
               <p>THe Lords diſcharges the Clerk to the Bills to expede the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioned Suſpenſion, untill the Chargers be heard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> Ordinar; to whom they remit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the reaſons of Suſpenſion upon the Bill: By which delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (paſſing the Soleſiſme therein contained, in diſcharging the Clerk to expede the Bill who never had power to expede a Bill till it was paſſed by the Lords, and by the latter part of it make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it impoſſible for either Lord or Clerk to expede it, in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Suſpenſion; It being remitted to the Ordinar to diſcuſs the reaſons upon the Bill) <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> had theſe Advantages, <hi>1mo,</hi> The choice of his own Lord, how much he followed my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his Faith ſhall appear by what follows hereafter: <hi>2do,</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he prejudged us of the benefit of the Roll, which by the Laws of the Kingdom, and Immemorial Pratick, is allowed to all the Leidges. <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> Hereby we were prejudged of the ordinar dyets, Competent to Defenders in purſuts for Mails and Deuties, in ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45333:9"/>far as upon the 25 of <hi>Januarie,</hi> we were ordained to produce our Intereſts with Certification betwixt and the tenth of <hi>Februarie</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: Which was the allowing us but 16 dayes, which in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, if we had had the benefit of the Roll, and other Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges Competent to Defenders, in Actions for Mails and Dueties, would have been 16 Moneths; A great part of our righs being out of our hands, whereupon an incident diligence would have been granted us. But howſoever this being inacted, wee reſted ſecure, till an Act ſhould have been extracted, as has been the conſtant practiſe in all ſuch caſes, ever ſince the erection of the Colledge of Juſtice: Ane therefore we payed the Extracter to give us out a Scrol to ſee, before the ſame ſhould be Subſcrived. But the day being elapſed, the Ordinar called it upon the Bench, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Act extracted; and becauſe we did not inſtantly produce Decerned, preferring <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> to the Mails and Duties, whereupon we put in another Bill, of the Tenor following,</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <p>MY Lords of Council and Seſſion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto your Lordſhips, Humbly Means and ſhaws, we your Servitors <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> Conjunct Fiar of the Lands of <hi>Killernie,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Robert Pittilloch</hi> her Husband, That whereas <hi>Alexander Altoun</hi> of <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> having raiſed a ſummonds for Mails and Duties againſt our Tennants, after the day of Compearance was paſt, and Tennants and we were both ready to Anſwer, he changed the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his Action unto a Suſpenſion of double Poynding (as is humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) contrare to Law and Equity, hereby prejudging us of the priviledges allowed to all the Lieges, in ſuch caſes by Acts of Parliament, Acts of Sede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, and immemorial Pratick: Notwithſtanding hereof, we in an intire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to your Lordſhips pleaſure, ſubmitted thereto, providing your Lordſhips would ordain him to ſubſcrive and abide by the ſaid Bill ſtuffed with calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious untruths, prejudicial both to us and our Tennants, and therefore diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſclaimed by them. And that your Lordſhips would grant us and our Tennants the ſame priviledges, which in Law are allowed to all his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects in purſutes for Mails and Duties, this being no other but the ſame Action <hi>in omnibus mutato nomine.</hi> Albeit as to the firſt, your Lordſhips referred the cauſing him ſubſcrive and abide by the Bill to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar to whom it was firſt preſented, there is nothing done therein, and as to the other, when after your Lordſhips had enacted us to produce our intereſts <hi>hinc inde,</hi> the tenth of <hi>February,</hi> in regard whereof, upon good and Legal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45333:10"/>Grounds, we reſted ſecure till an Act ſhould have been extracted, calling for a ſcroll thereof often in the Clerks Chamber, with a purpoſe to give ready obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in place thereof by an unuſual ſurpriſal, without an Act, we were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained inſtantly to produce, which we could not do. And becauſe we did it not, a Decreet was preſently put up againſt us, in regard whereof, we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive it ought to be Declared by your Lordſhips, whether any Proceſs ought to be ſuſtained upon this Bill, before the Purſuer ſubſcrive the ſame, and abide thereat. And 2dly, Whether your Lordſhips will ſuſtain this for a practick, that where there is an Act paſſed, there can be either a Decreet of Preference or Circumduction of the Terme, before Extracting and Calling the Act? And if your Lordſhips find it can ſubſiſt with Law and Forme, we ſhall inſtantly produce.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore, may it pleaſe your Lordſhips, to take the premiſes to your ſerious conſideration, and to give us your poſitive Determination thereanent, and to Declare whether we and our Tennants ſhall have the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of other Defenders, purſued for Mails and Duties, or if the ſame ſhall be Arbitrarlie altered in favours of <hi>Inchdarnie,</hi> becauſe this Action hath gotten the name of a Suſpenſion; And in the mean time to ordain the Decreet abovementioned to be expunged.</p>
                     <p>The Deliverance and Anſwer whereunto, was in theſe Terms.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>Februarie</hi> l8th. 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>The Lords having heard this Bill, remits to the Ordinar, who paſsed the Bill of Suſpenſion to allow the Petitioners a farder Terme to produce their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or not, as he ſhall find juſt.</p>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>If the Lords had refuſed or rejected this Bill, as frivolous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent; it is like the Petitioners ſubmitting to their Lordſhips Judgements, would have acquieſced. But as the things therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, are in themſelves pregnant, and moſt pertinent, ſo the Lords implicitly at leaſt, have approven them to be ſuch: by giving them ſome thing like an anſwer; but in effect anſwering none of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars petitioned for in the Bill. For albeit it may be alleaged, that a farder Dyet was craved in this Bill; It is eaſily anſwered, that albeit by the granting the juſt deſires of this Bill, it would have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Conſequence, that a further Term would have been granted, yet this is no wayes the deſire of the Bill; but <hi>1mo,</hi> That <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> ſubſcrive the Bill, and abide thereat, that a ſolid ground
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45333:10"/>might be laid of an improbation againſt him for his Falſet and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. <hi>2do,</hi> That the Circumduction of the Term might be declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Null; That ſo that Decreet might be turned into a Lybell: and no Circumduction might paſs till an Act were Extracted, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, conform to the Laws of the Kingdom. <hi>3tio,</hi> That the Lords would declare, they would allow us the Priviledges due to other Defenders, in actions for Mails and Deuties: Or if the ſame ſhould be Arbitrarly altered, in favours af <hi>Inchdairnie,</hi> becauſe it has the name of a Suſpenſion.</p>
               <p>But all Petitions being in vain, we produced <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> her ſeaſin, bearing her to be infeſt in the Lands above ſpecified: Which was all the Rights we had in the Town at that time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe Lands. And <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> produced his Rights, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, whereupon we were ordained to ſee in the Clerks hands: tho' the ordinar Cuſtome according to Law, and practice, is to ſend out the purſuers proceſs, to the Defenders Advocate: Which he is not bound to return till ſix dayes be Elapſed, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender is not tyed to produce his, till he propone thereupon, and if his Defence Founded upon his Intereſt be founded Relivant, a day is aſſigned to him, whereupon the Purſuer extracts an Act, and forces him to produce. But as to the Purſuers Production, we were only ordained to ſee in the Clerks hands, who refuſed to give it up without a receipt from our Advocate: Which being grented, before or a little after twenty four hours were elapſed; (a time ſcarce Competent to Inventar the many writes given in by the Purſuer) we were urged to deliver them back again: tho' ours is keept up to this day. <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> pretending it is his evident; And an Action of Removeing Depending againſt us; tho' this was the only evident we had whereupon to found a Defence; And albeit his Father in Law, and Procutor had declared; there ſhould no ſuch Action be purſued till it were given up, adding they were not ſo baſe, as to fight with a man when they had taken his Armes from him.</p>
               <p>The production being thus ſatisfied, My Lord <hi>Drumcairn</hi> called it upon the Bench: Where my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> compeared with his Purple Gown, and debated the caſe as <hi>Inchdairnies</hi> Advocat, repeating all his writs, it ſeems relying on the old Proverb, <hi>Quum ſingula non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, multa juvant.</hi> But ſo far as I remember there paſt no <hi>Decreet</hi> that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45333:11"/>day, but to morrow thereafter his Lordſhip calle it again, at the Side Bar; where my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> compeared again, in his former habit, and the diſpute was renewed: in which diſpute, our Advocates would propone nothing as to the Annualrents, aled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged due by the Infeſtments following upon the Heritable Bonds: Becauſe an Action for ſuch Annualrents, and an Action for Mails Deuties, are <hi>toto caelo</hi> different, <hi>2dly,</hi> Becauſe there was nothing in <hi>Libello:</hi> There being nothing in the Bill of Suſpenſion, which was the ground of the Proceſs, but Mails and Deuties: But knowing there could be nothing in this proceſs for a ground of Mails and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are the Emolument of the property, but the Appriſing; This unanſwerable Defence was proponed: Offers to prove the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing Reduced, <hi>in foro contradictorio, quo ad Margaret Wardlaw,</hi> the Conjunct-fiar, and tho they were bound to ſay no further; Yet <hi>ex ſuper abundanti,</hi> becauſe what he proponed upon a Back-bond of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, ſeemed to ſavour much of Natural Equity: It was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>primo,</hi> This Back bond was granted by a Wife, <hi>ſtante Matrimonio,</hi> and under Reduction, <hi>2do:</hi> Finding there was much weight laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, we offered under proteſtation that it ſhould not be prejudicial to our Reduction, to Count and Reckon preſently, without an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Redemption; Albeit in Law without an Order, we were not tyed to Anſwer. To the firſt it was replyed, the Reduction is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice of <hi>Inchdarnies</hi> Authors real Right, which <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> produced to clear the ſame, which was true as to the matter, but moſt impertinent as an anſwer to the Defence produced: It was not contraverted but their real Rights were valid; but they could never be a ground for Mails and Duties <hi>in prima inſtantia;</hi> nor any other Right they produced but the Appryſing, which the Defence above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, did totally elied. But my Lord <hi>Drumcairn</hi> being ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Defence, anſwered himſelf, that our Reduction was but as to perſonal Execution againſt <hi>Margaret Wardlaw.</hi> To which I replyed my ſelf, my Lord, <hi>The peril of the cauſe upon that.</hi> And hear we deſire the Judicious Reader to conſider, whether the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinar who gave ſuch an Anſwer, had puruſed the proceſs, or if <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicita fide,</hi> he had followed my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his Faith: ſeeing the very words of the Reduction are, <hi>Finds the firſt Reaſon of Reduction re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livant, and proven, to ſo far as concerns the perſonal Obligdment, and all that has followed, or may follow thereupon as Null; And therefore, Reduces, Retreats,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45333:11"/>Caſſis, and Annuls the ſaids Bands, in ſo far as they perſonally obliege the ſaid</hi> Margaret Wardlaw, <hi>with all Decreets of Appriſings, Charters, Seaſings, Decreets of Removing following thereupon, Declaring the ſame to have been from the beginning, to be now and in all time coming Void, and of none Effect,</hi> quo ad eam, <hi>in ſo far as the ſamen are deduced againſt her, upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid perſonal Oblidgement.</hi> Likeas if his Lordſhips patience would have admitted us a Hearing, we could ſhewed him further, that ſhe ſtood in no need of a Security for her perſon; in regard the ſame was already ſufficiently ſecured, by a Suſpenſion ſtanding yet undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed. To the ſecond, there was nothing anſwered, <hi>But there was no Reduction produced;</hi> which was an Anſwer of no value, it being time competent enough to produce it, at any time before the Count and Reckoning was ended: Eſpecially the ſame being offered, before uſeing an order of Redemption, or raiſing Declarator thereon. But my Lord without further anſwer, or heeding what was ſaid, decerned, and ſo went haſtily from the <hi>Side Barr,</hi> refuſing us the Lords Anſwer upon a Maund; which in Law is competent to all Subjects in the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Hereupon to morrow thereafter, I put in a Bill to the Lords, of the Tennor following:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <p>MY Lords of Council and Seſſion, unto your Lordſhips humbly Means and Shews; We your Servitors <hi>Margaret Wardlaw,</hi> Conjunct Fiar of the Lands of <hi>Killernie</hi> and <hi>Bandrum,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Robert Pittilloch</hi> Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, her Hushand for his Intereſt. That whereas on <hi>Friday</hi> the <hi>24,</hi> of this Inſtant, My Lord <hi>Drumcairn</hi> at the <hi>Side Barr</hi> paſt a Decreet in favours of <hi>Inchdarnie,</hi> preferring him to the Dueties of the ſaids Lands: For the Demonſtrating the Iniquitie of this Sentance, Your Petitioners conceives it their duty, to Repreſent to your Lordſhips the whole tract of this Affair, which is as follows, <hi>viz. Inchdarnie</hi> having fain in by an unexpected Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to ſome Mails and Deuties alleged, reſting to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Stewarts,</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles to the Laird of <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> having ſent for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Robert,</hi> under pretence of Agreement therefore, and received from him theſe Rational Anſwers: That he could not make any Agreement for any Mails and Dueties, till he had agreed with <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> in whoſe perſon the Heritable Right ſtood, becauſe it would not only be an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologating</hi> of <hi>Roſſyths</hi> Right, but the paying out of Mails and Dueties for a <hi>Liferentrix.</hi> For the return whereof he had no aſſurance, by reaſon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45333:12"/>of the uncertaintie of her Life, and that he was in terms with <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> for the Heritable right in order to Agreement, for what Mails and Dueties ſhould be found due. In place of expecting the cloſe of this Agreement which your Petitioners haſtned, they being in terms before to this purpoſe, rationally to have ſatitfied his Lordſhip. <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> with concourſe of my Lord <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carſe,</hi> his Father in Law, after your Petitioners had verbally agreed with <hi>Roſſyth,</hi> for the ſaid heretable Right, and it was concluded it ſhould be drawn in write with all poſſible conveniencie, cauſed him diſpone his Right to his ſaid Son in I am for a <hi>1000.</hi> Merks <hi>Scots</hi> leſs then your Petitioner had agreed, for he having a great Action depending in the Seſſion againſt my Lord <hi>Annandale;</hi> and knowing the great Figure <hi>Hercarſe</hi> made amongſt the Lords. <hi>2ly.</hi> Having obtained this Right, his Son in Law raiſed ſummonds againſt your Petitioners and their Tennants for Mails and Duties in which Action, we were moſt ready and willing to have anſwered him according to the Laws and practick of the Kingdom, but inſtead thereof, in an unuſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, after the day of Compearance was paſt, he raiſed a Suſpenſion of double Poynding in the Tennants names, which (at we are informed by able Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, was never ſuſtained but in favours of Suſpenders really diſtreſſed by Chargers to be diſcuſſed upon a Bill, when they could not find caution: Farr leſs at the inſtance of the Purſuers, when the alledged Suſpenders diſclaimed and diſowned the ſame, under their hands. As alſo, your Petitioners al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Chargers on the other part, Diſowned the ſame. <hi>3dly.</hi> When the ſaids Tennants did put in a Bill, Craving, That in regard they had diſowned the ſame, and that it was filled with calumnious untruths, it might be either given up to them, as their own proper Evident, to be cancelled; or at leaſt <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> might be ordained to ſubſcrive the ſame before witneſſes, and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliter</hi> abide thereat, whereby they are prejudged of their Improbation, the remedie of Law in ſuch caſes. <hi>4ly.</hi> That in all Actions for Mails and Due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (of which nature this is <hi>mutato ſolummodo nomine</hi>) no Decreet can in Law be pronounced where a terme is aſſigned for producing an Intereſt for diſobedience, till an Act be Extracted and after Extracting, Called, and the Terme Circumduced for not Production; Yet in this Action before an Act was Extracted, a Decreet was pronounced, while your Petitioners upon Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal grounds reſted ſecure, and had given money to the Extracter for a ſight of a ſcroll of the Act, when it was called by their Adverſary, my Lord <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> paſt a Decreet of Preference in favours of <hi>Inchdarnie. 5thly.</hi> His Lordſhip upon an Addreſs made to him ſince we produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Margaret. Wardlaws</hi> Infefiment, having called this Action
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45333:12"/>again, we proponed an unanſwerable Defence, why <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> could not be preferred, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Appryſing which was the ground of all, the Proceſs was reduced <hi>quo ad Margaret Wardlaw,</hi> My Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> Procurator for <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> anſwered, that our Reduction did not prove our Alledgance, and that be would produce the ſame himſelf, and added that there was an Backhand of Reverſion granted to <hi>Andrew Wardlaw,</hi> whoſe Right ſtood in <hi>Inchdarnies</hi> perſon, which made it appear that <hi>Margaret Wardlaw</hi> is payed, for all that ſhe could crave out of this Eſtate: To which it was replyed, that the Defence being unqueſtionably Relevant, the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to admitted to the Proponer, at leaſt if he produced the Decreet of Reduction, which was made uſe of for proving our Defence, we ought to ſee and be heard to object againſt it. And as to the Band of Reverſion, it was anſwered it was granted by her <hi>tante Matrimonio</hi> meerly for Love and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and under Reduction long after ſhe ſtood publickly infeſt. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> My Lord <hi>Drumcairn</hi> having called this Action again after he had tak n the Diſpute above mentioned to a <hi>viſandum,</hi> My Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> ſtill compear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Procurator for his Son in Law (a Practick without a paralel) without giving us a ſight of the Decreet they produced to object againſt it or admitting us Accompt or Reckoning in referrence to the Reverſion, which we offered under proteſtation it ſhould not be prejudicial to our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reduction, ſtill decerned accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deſire of My Lord <hi>Hercarſe, Inchdarnies</hi> Procurator, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to the Mails and Dueties.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore we humbly pray that your Lordſhips for ſhunning the guilt of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Sentence, and for vindicating your own Honours before the World, would ſeriouſly conſider the Concuſſions, the overhailings, the Injuries, the Illegalities, and Informalities of the ſaid Proceſs, and particulars deduced therein, tending to the ruin of your Petitioners, without any free hearing or the benefit which by the Laws of the Kingdom is allowed to all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects, and diſcharge the Extracting of any ſuch Decreet, till your Petitioners be heard fully and freely to debate their Intereſts as others his Majeſties Subjects uſes to be heard in ſuch caſes.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Bill being read to the Lords, It is given up to my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> to ſee: Who (as is informed) went to the Kings Advocat, and conſulced it, to make up a ſtrong Accuſation againſt the ingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Who was appointed to anſwer to the Bill on <hi>Tueſday</hi> thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, upon which the ſame being called the ſaid day, in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the Lords gave their Deliverance in thir Terms:</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45333:13"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="response">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Lords finds the Repreſentations contained in the ſaid Bill Calumnious, and therefore refuſes the deſire of the ſaid Supplication, and ordains</hi> Macers <hi>and</hi> Meſſangers at Arms, <hi>to apprehend the ſaid Mr.</hi> Robert, <hi>and incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerat his Perſon till further Order.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Which Sentence in this was the more grievous, that it was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Penult day of the Seſſion, ſo that if he had been Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended on the morrow thereafter, he muſt have lyen in Priſon till the ſitting down of the next Seſſion, being the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no one Lord nor three would have taken upon them to have inlarged him. But taking this Deliverance into my ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, I found it 1ſt. Generally finding the Repreſentations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Bill Calumnious: And I humbly conceive, there are ſome of them, which my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> himſelf will not avert to be Calumnious: <hi>2dly,</hi> I found there was no mention of the latter part of the deliverance, anent my impriſonment, mentioned in the Decreet, when the ſaid Deliverance is repeated for fortifying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Laſtly.</hi> I find none of our Bills, firſt or laſt, inſert in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, nor the Anſwers thereto, tho it be the conſtant cuſtome in ſuch caſes, alwayes to inſert Bills and Anſwers as a part of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: Which Fortifies or Weakens, as they are Granted, or Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; And as to the Reaſon hereof, I leave it to the Judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and will not take upon me to judge thereof, leaſt it be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me for a ſecond Crime; But come to the Bill it ſelf: The firſt Repreſentation bears, the Conference which paſt betwixt my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> and the Petitioner, when he firſt ſent for him; And that albeit the Petitioner haſtened the Agreement, <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> with concourſe of his Father in Law, after the ſame was done, cauſed him diſpone it to him for a 1000. Merks leſs than I had agreed for; He having a great Action depending in the Seſſion, againſt my Lord <hi>Annandale,</hi> and knowing the great Figure <hi>Hercarſe</hi> made among the Lords. As to what touching the firſt part of it, anent our Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, it is believed <hi>Hercarſe</hi> will not deny the Truth, of it himſelf, and there is no ſhaddow of a Calumnie in it. As to the 2d: part of it, That <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> cauſed him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſnone with concourſe of his Father in Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We hope my Lord will not deny he was preſent, at the making of the Bargain, which if he do, we offer to prove it: And if he was preſent, all the World will conclude he came not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45333:13"/>there as a Cipher. Yea, we are free to ſay, any Man who knows him and his Son in Law both, ſpeaking his mind with any ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, will conclude he was the chief Actor. That <hi>Roſſyth</hi> had a great Action depending before the Lords, againſt my Lord <hi>Annandail,</hi> is nottour; and I have often heard it of himſelf. And that <hi>Hercarſe</hi> made a great Figure among the Lords, is no leſs nottour. The Bill bears neither that my Lord promiſed to haſten his Action for the Bargain; nor to do him any good office whatſoever, but ſimplie relates the Truth as it was: And if my Lord himſelf makes any ſuch Applications, he may blame the witneſs within himſelf, and not the Ingiver of the Bill: Tho he believes it had been neither ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie, nor reflecting upon my Lord, tho he had added, <hi>Roſſyth having in his view the ſervice ſuch a Lord might do him, farr beyond the worth of</hi> 1000. <hi>Merks or two.</hi> The ſecond Repreſentation is, That in an unuſual manner, he raiſed a Suſpenſion in the Tennants names, which was by them and the other alledged Chargers diſowned, which as we are informed, is not agreeable to Law. If it be uſual we deſire the Complainer to condeſcend but upon three caſes (which is the leaſt makes a perfect number) quadrating with this ſince the Erection of the Colledge of Juſtice, and we ſhall acknowledge it an Error, tho it would prove no calumnie; but a miſtake of the Form of Proceſs before the Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if it be denyed, that it was diſowned by the Tennants, it is offered to be proven <hi>ſcripto;</hi> and the Anſwers given in to <hi>Inchdarnies</hi> Bill ſufficiently verifies, it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned by one of the Chargers, and their carriage all along in the whole buſineſs. As to the third, That the Tennants put in a Bill, craving the Bill of Suſpenſion might be given up to them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; or that <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> might be ordained to ſubſcribe the ſame before Witneſſes, and abide thereat. If it be denyed, their Bill is Extant to verifie it: And that it was not granted, is a Negative, and proves it ſelt, till the contrar be inſtructed. As to the Fourth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, it is, that where in an Action for Mails and Dueties it is enacted that the Defender produce ſuch a day, no Decreet can be pronounced, till an Act be Extracted, and called, yet without Extracting and calling an act, this Decreet was Pronounced: And as to the firſt part thereof, there is hardly a Pock bearer about the houſe, but will give Teſtimony to the Truth of it; and as to the ſecond, it is beliered the ordinar will not deny he paſt a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45333:14"/>upon the Bench; when there was no act extracted: tho' after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he paſt it <hi>de-novo</hi> upon as was alledged better Grounds: To which many others likewiſe were witneſſes. The fifth Reprſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation contains nothing, but an Abbreviat of the Diſput', and that my <hi>Lord Hercarſe</hi> compeared as Procurator for <hi>Inchdairnie:</hi> If it be denyed that <hi>Hercarſe</hi> compeared as Procurator, we are ready to prove it by many witneſſes: That we proponed the Defence mentioned in the Bill, and gave in the replyes ſpecified therein to <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his anſwers, we offer to prove it if denyed by <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his own oath, he being now but a private perſon, and the Declaration of my Lord <hi>Drumcairn.</hi> The laſt Repreſentation is, that tho' we offered to compt and reckon without an order of Redemption it was not granted; And that we never had a ſight of the Decreet <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carſe</hi> proponed upon; For eleiding our Defence; That the Aprry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing was reduced, which we offer to prove by the oath af <hi>Hercarſe</hi> and the Declaration of my Lord <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> and that <hi>Hercarſe</hi> was ſtill Procurator, for ſhame will not be denyed: Yea only Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in this Debate. And that it was a Practick without a Paralel, we alſo repreſented, which we ſhall acknowledge for an Error, but no Calumnie, when the contrair is inſtructed: We have ſeen a Lord come to the Barr, when his own cauſe was debating, but behav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf with ſuch Modeſty, that hardly would he meddle in the Diſpute, or any thing, unleſs it had been to inform in the matter of Fact, but referred all to his Advocats: But for a Lord to come to the Bar, and debate as Procurator for another man, is indeed that which we never either heard or ſaw, and as to the Precatory part which deſires the Lords to conſider the concuſſions, the overhailings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is anſwered , 1ſt. Tho therein there were ſomething, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſert in the Narrative might inferr Calumnie; Yet the ſcop of the Petitioning part, being meerly to deſire the Lords to conſider, if things be ſo and ſo, and to rectifie as they ſhall find cauſe: It would be very hard to declare upon a miſtake here, the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to be guilty of Calumnie: There is never a Bill put in, which is a complaint, but craves ſomething to be rectified, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently complains, at leaſt Implicirly of Injuſtice; And if it be not in Terms ſufficiently flattering, they muſt excuſe me for this Error: I will not give Flattering Titles unto Man willingly, <hi>leaſt my Maker take me away ſuddenly: Job</hi> 31. ver. 21. But <hi>2dly,</hi> We believe we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45333:14"/>have ſufficiently inſtructed injurie, which in the largeſt ſenſe, is <hi>quicquid fit non jure,</hi> overhailing, by precipitating Judgment, Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie, and Informality, in carrying on the Action in a way una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Laws of the Land: And that there was concuſſion is ſufficiently made out, in ſhewing the way, how <hi>Inchdarnie</hi> came to the Bargain, to which we now add: <hi>My Lords</hi> ingaging the <hi>King's Advocat</hi> in the cauſe, <hi>unde abuſus eſt patronatu Caeſaris;</hi> Labouring to make it a publick concernment, and his influencing the Ordinar ſo much to follow his Faith: Upon pretence of his great skill in Law, whom the Ordinar conceived to be of as great Ingenuity as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And if it be alledged that he could not <hi>injicere terrorem,</hi> in the Ordinar; who was of equal ſtation with himſelf, and <hi>Cuſſing Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to my Lady <hi>Errol,</hi> a great Courtier in that day, by reaſon of Communon with the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi> It is anſwered, granting that he was not only of equal ſtation with my <hi>Lord Hercarſe,</hi> but alſo that his Mountain was preſumed to ſtand ſtrong in that day; becauſe of his near Relation to my Lady <hi>Errol</hi> a Profeſſed <hi>Papiſt,</hi> by whoſe Moyan likewayes many believed he was preferred to his place; but all fear upon Concuſſion, is not a ſlaviſh fear whereof we judge my Lord <hi>Drumcairn</hi> was leaſt capable: but there might be a fear of being toped by <hi>Hercarſe,</hi> when matters came to be Debate in the <hi>Inner-houſe,</hi> and a fear of loſing his Friendſhip, with whom he was very Intimat. Neither is <hi>Concuſſion</hi> alwayes taken in ſo narrow a ſenſe, as importing only a ſlaviſh fear: <hi>Cod: Tit: de Concuſſione le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge</hi> 4. <hi>Jubemus atque hortamur ut ſi quis forte honoratorum de curionum poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsorum poſtremo etiam colonorum, aut cujuſlibet ordinis a judice fuerit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua ratione concuſſus, ſi quis ſcit vaenalem fuiſſe de jure Sententiam; ſi quis poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam vel pretio remiſſam vel vitio cupiditatis injeſtam, ſi quis poſtremo quacun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que de cauſa improbum jndicem potuerit improbare is vel adminiſtrante eo, vel poſt adminiſtrationem depoſitam in publicum, prodeat crimen deferat delatum approbet cum probaverit &amp; victoriam reportaturus &amp; Gloriam.</hi> To all which may be added, that while we ſpeak be way of complaint of my Lord <hi>Hercarſe;</hi> we ſpake againſt him not as a <hi>Lord of the Seſſion,</hi> but as <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> his Procurator, if a Lord of the Seſſion, ſhould be found in a <hi>Plebeian</hi> habit, in ſome baſe imployment, and meet with ſome afront which would be eſteemed ſuch to a Lord; but not to one of a vulgar ſtation, he could not complain that there were any injurie done, or a Lord were affronted: And therefore though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45333:15"/>there were ſomething in this Bill which might be quarrelled if done againſt a Lord: (which we cannot find) Sure there is nothing in it which might not have been ſaid, againſt a Procurator, and more alſo.</p>
               <p>But poſſible it will be alledged, I am preſumed to be guilty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was no Compearance for me, In anſwer to which it is to be conſidered, the order was that I ſhould compear on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> to anſwer to my Bill, (which whither it was publick or not I do not remember) which according to the Grammatical Conſtruction, and the letter, ſeems to be in my favours; for explaining and clearing ſomething in the Bill, and taken in this ſenſe; I might compear or not, as I thought good: For any man may renounce <hi>jus ſuum,</hi> but I ſoon found it was in the ſcope of it, to anſwer to <hi>Hercarſe</hi> his Accuſations, founded upon my Bill, in which caſe I was not tyed to compear: till Firſt, they had given me notice who was my Accuſer, <hi>2do.</hi> The double of my Inditement, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it being founded upon write, and a Complex buſineſs. <hi>3tio,</hi> I ought to have been Cited by a <hi>Macer</hi> or <hi>Meſſengers at Arms,</hi> none whereof were done: And therefore I was not bound to compear; And yet I did compear, and was ready to anſwer all the Forenoon, but they delayed the calling of it till the Afternoon; at which time I judged it no wayes mv duty to compear, for theſe reaſons, 1ſt. In the Afternoon the Officers of State are Abſent, <hi>2do.</hi> All the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Lords are abſent who were unconcerned in the Buſineſs: <hi>3tio.</hi> It was impoſſible for me to get my Advocat whom I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, to attend in the Afternoon, in the cloſe of the Seſſion, he being a Gentleman of great Imployment; and it was uncertain whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would call at 2. or 3. a Clock ot at 6. or 7. at Night. So much for the Clamercus Bill, ſo called.</p>
               <p>Within a few dayes after the riſing of the Seſſion, the Lords meeting for ſome concernment of their own, They recommended to the <hi>Preſident</hi> to agree the Civil Intereſt, and for that effect delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Execution of the Sentence, for my Impriſonment for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, with power to my Lord Preſident to prolong my Liberty if he ſhould find cauſe therefore. Hereupon we made an Addreſs to my Lord <hi>Hercarſe,</hi> to draw an Abſolute Submiſſion to my <hi>Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident,</hi> to do in the matter as he ſhould find juſt: To which <hi>Hercarſe</hi> chearfully condeſcended, being then in a tender frame, partly through the reſcent loſe of his Place, and partly through the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45333:15"/>and death of his Daughter, who if Fame be not a falſe witneſs, was a Gentlewoman qualified with ſingular Induments: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we cauſed draw the Submiſſion and ſubſcrived it, I my ſelf and my wife, who was going out of the Town, <hi>Hercaſe</hi> having declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (becauſe <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> was not in Town) he would take burden for him. But it being uncivility to trouble him, while he was in <hi>extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate luctus,</hi> we forbear for a time, and when we came to deſire he would ſubſcrive, found he was returned to his old Temper, and he reſiled, alledging a Communing would do the buſineſs, and when we told this to the <hi>Preſident,</hi> we found him of the ſame mind, and albeit I well knew a Communing would be to no purpoſe, yet that it might appear I was averſe from nothing which might effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at Peace, I attended a moneth after the Seſſion roſe; being in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry infirme and Valetudinarie condition, in which at length hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained a meeting before the <hi>Preſident,</hi> I found nothing in his Comuning but Calumnniating my Perſon, and juſtifying all he had done: But concluding that they might get theſe Lands with a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, he would give what the <hi>Preſident</hi> ſhould appoint. But not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with his rough diſcourſe, and knowing he might as well reſeill from the <hi>Preſidents</hi> determination by word, as he did from the Submiſſion: We parted without a Concluſion, only the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident</hi> ſaid, he would order his Decreet to be extracted, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly was done.</p>
               <p>This being done, <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> with <hi>John Law, Hercaſe</hi> his Servant, went alongſt the Tennents, and with many Threatnings and bigg Menacing words perſwaded them to take their Lands holden of him. But all in vain, their love to their old Maſters was ſo deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they would take of no other, till neceſſity forced them: Hereupon <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> in <hi>July</hi> thereafter charged them, to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Mails and Dueties as he had lybelled them in his Bill of Suſpenſion; upon 15 days: But his Charge being given upon the 6. of <hi>July,</hi> they were denounced upon the 11. which was upon 5. days, all Regiſtrate at the <hi>Horn,</hi> and <hi>Caption</hi> taken out againſt them. Whereupon (as is informed) <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> was upon his way, to have taken all the Tennents, but his Father in Law knowing the groſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Act, ſent over <hi>Mr. Law</hi> and ſtoped him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And to Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Illegial Denunciation, and Caption, which was taken out, he and his Guide abovementioned, came to the <hi>Tennents,</hi> and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45333:16"/>them, if they brought not their Dutie to him, and that to his own houſe before the 15 days were expired, he ſhould not leave them a Cock to crow Day: And (as is informed) his Father in Law took the <hi>Meſsenger</hi> to the <hi>Preſident,</hi> who being a poor man took all the fault upon himſelf; giving an Excuſe therefore, not worthy of the writing, and far leſs of an Anſwer. But one thing was forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them both, the ſame <hi>Meſſenger</hi> was thereafter imployed to apprehend the <hi>Tennents,</hi> which no rational man being free of the guilt, would have done; he being ſo groſs a <hi>Criminal,</hi> untill he had either been Purged, or Puniſhed. But the <hi>Tennnents</hi> finding that the charge it ſelf was judged Illegal, by ſeveral Writers to the <hi>Signet,</hi> it being but in effect a general preferrence, and a Declarator of <hi>Inch-Inchdairnies</hi> right, a Bill was put in to the Lords, complaining upon the writter, who had raiſed ſuch a Horning, they being charged particularly, for the Sumes as <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> had lybeled them. To which the anſwer was, <hi>finds the Writter has done no wrong:</hi> Hereupon the Fifteen dayes being near expired, a Bill was put in in the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents names, for a Suſpenſion, as the laſt remeed, whereof the reaſons were. 1ſt. The generality of the Charge (for the Charger diſowned the particular Charges given by the <hi>Meſsenger.</hi>) <hi>2do.</hi> There was no Liquidation, tho ſome of their Dueties were partly Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. <hi>3tio,</hi> There was no probation of the quantities. <hi>4to.</hi> There were ſeveral others not called, who had an Intereſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The Superior for the few Duties, and the Miniſter, and School-maſter for their Stipends: Which Bill was given up to ſee, and kept up till the laſt day of the Seſſion, that in caſe there were any neceſſity for it, all remeed might be cut off. The reaſons were unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Relivant, and paſſing by the laſt, the 3 firſt were inſtantly proven being Negatives; all that ever ſaw it concluded, it could no be refuſed, but if it had been paſt, it would have coſt <hi>Hercarſe</hi> a ſecond Bellum, and it was too ſtrong to be refuſed. A new courſe is invented, for fortifying <hi>Inchdarnies</hi> Decreet, (whether by <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carſe</hi> his contrivance or not, we leave it to the Reader to judge.) The <hi>Lords</hi> ordained the Tennents to compear in time of Vaccan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>viz.</hi> Betwixt and the 15 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> before my <hi>Lord Caſtlehill,</hi> and depone anent the ſpecies and quantities who had no Tacks: and ſuch as had tacks to produce, and reſtricked the Chargers diligence, to what u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Oath they ſhould depone, and to what was contained in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45333:16"/>their Tacks who had any. Which Sentence is never drawn in an Act, Extracted and Read out of the Minut-Book, to put the Tennents in <hi>Mala fide;</hi> But Writen by the Clerk upon a Lords Direction, ſeveral dayes after the riſing of the <hi>Seſſion:</hi> Yea ſo cloſe it was in the carrying of it on, that the Gentel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who was Agent in the cauſe, having inquired of it at the Clerk, he told him he could not tell him what it was, nor could I my ſelf by any inquiry, have certainty in the matter, till I came to my Lord <hi>Caſtlehill</hi> hearing it ſurmiſed, it was referred to him as it was indeed. Hereupon the Tennents did compear, and produced there Tacks and Deponed: Only two ſent Teſtificats ſubſcrived by the Miniſter, and four Elders, witneſſing that in regard of their great Age they were not fit for Travel, the one being upwards of Fourſcore years, and the other being near about this Age: Which was not ſuſtained becauſe it wanted <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> concerning which we ſhall only ſay this much, that albeit it be ordinar, in Teſt ficats under the hands of Phyſicians and Chirurgions, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire they be upon Soul and Conſcience: It was never required in a Teſtificat, concerning a Mans Age, for if ſo the Teſtifiers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves muſt be about a Hundred, which is rare in this Age: For he cannot give <hi>rationem ſcientiae</hi> till he be Fourteen; and ſecondly they muſt have been witneſſes either to his Birth or Baptiſm 80 years agoe. But we leave thir tickliſh queſtions to my Lord <hi>Hercarſe</hi> to ſolve. The Tennents having ſome deponed, and ſome produred their Tacks <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> denunced them regiſtrare and took out Caption <hi>de novo,</hi> and upon the 21 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the ſame Meſſenger, at his inſtance apprehended the Tennents; being ten in number, whereof two were the old men abovementioned, and incarcerat them in the Tolbooth of <hi>Dunfermling:</hi> W ere they continu d Priſoners ten dayes, being the time of Harveſt: till they were forced to pay him their Dueties; ſuch as could get Money, and ſuch as could not to give Bond, or find Caution, as alſo after they had agreed for their Duetie, he forced them to take a three years Tack of him, or elſe threatned them to return them again to Priſon.</p>
               <p>How the Lords will reliſh this diligence, before advſing of the Tennents oaths, and a Declaration judicial what was contained in their Tacks, time will declare hereafter: But we believe up n im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Examination, it will be found a clear Spulzie, and alſo a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45333:17"/>breach of Arreſtment, there being two Arreſtments layed on upon the Mails and Duties, which were not looſed by <hi>Inchdairnie,</hi> till the Tennents were brought Priſoners to the Town of <hi>Dunfermling.</hi> The Chancellour his Over-awing power being now gone with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, tho' not long ſince, <hi>Inchdairnie</hi> foread out his kindly Letter to him, before the Tennents in <hi>Tillo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ill,</hi> to terrifie them by his Authority.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:45333:17"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
